hello I'm your host David Barnard
today's conversation is shorter than
usual and will be featured in Revenue
cat state of subscription apps report
each episode in this series will explore
one crucial metric and share actionable
insights from Top subscription app
operators with me today syvan Gus
director of Revenue strategy us at Babel
and chief insights minor at grams on the
podcast I talk with syon about top
strategies for paywall optimization the
danger of over optimizing and why the
screen before your pay wall might
actually matter more than your pay wall
hey saon thanks so much for joining me
on the podcast today hey D really
excited to be here I got some good stuff
for you looking forward to div in all
right you've been you've been mining
gems all year and I wanted to talk
through some of the best pay wall
related gems you've mined this year for
those who don't know syvan he run
something called growth gems where he
watches all the industry videos and
listens to podcast and then shares the
top tips mind's the gems from those so
let's kick it off what's your top gem
for 2024 on pay walls it's actually kind
of framing the discussion kind of gy
it's actually on everything leading to
the payall because I is if I don't talk
about that at all so the gem is from
Daryl Stone they used to be at CZ and so
the gem is get your users excited about
your product by telling the W Stone
through the flows that present the pay
wall think about the user mindset when
they open the app and the story you
reveal to them through the onboarding so
that when they see the pay wall it's
contextualized and I wanted to mention
that one because I consider the P really
the ask of the sale and if you don't
frame anything before you can try and
optimize it and you might get some wins
but you you're missing out so I I think
that story especially focusing on the
very beginning and kind of your hook in
the on boing and kind of the pick and
Rule of handing strong before the pay
wall is is what will make the pay wol
successful or a big part of it any
examples of apps that you think do an
incredible job leading up to the pay
wall yeah rise sleep is one that is
often mentioned I particularly like the
hook and kind of the story they tell at
the beginning same thing in terms of the
hook andle how we feel I discovered an
app yesterday called 222 that has like a
video essentially on boarding and hook
at the beginning that's pretty amazing
so yeah I think those those are doing
great awesome all right gem number two
gem number two it's about loss AV verion
as part of the onboarding have
onboarding questions then a generic pay
wall then more question related to
specific premium features or even have
users set up those premium features then
have a feature payall and say these are
part of the Premium plan the way that
works because you know to try and
explain it visually is essentially you
have people set up features throughout
the onboarding then you PR them with a
with a pill wall that essentially you
know it's like now get that get it and
if they don't get it you explain to them
everything they're going to lose and
they're going to essentially lose
everything that set they set up so
there's some some CA fallacy and the
idea is that the projects themselves
during onboarding you show that after
they reject the uh initial pay wall and
it's that last AV verion that pushes
them to convert yeah that's a great one
all right next gem next gem there are
multiple things you should test display
during the all experience a list of
features and explanation of how the free
trial Works social proof a comparison of
basic versus Pro Plan this can be done
for long scrollable screen or
multiscreen payall and this is from a
Catarina was at mimo and she was
mentioning that a mimo the multiscreen
option led to 60% increase in the trial
op rate and I've been seeing those
multiscreen pay walls more and more
especially for free trial where you know
instead of showing the blinkist timeline
they actually break it down down in
multiple screen to tell you what's going
to happen in 2 days what's going to
happen in 5 days Etc but it can work
also fun you know if you don't have a
free Tri and essentially what I like
about it I guess it's it blurs the line
between what's on boarding and what's a
payall it's like if you have a screen
before the pay wall is that part of the
onboarding is that part of the pay wall
but it gives you that possibility to
show benefits explain better the actual
like transactional aspect and have kind
of like some last minute pitch or recap
to push people over the edge yeah that's
such a great one as well I would guess
that part of why this works and this is
just maybe a truism that you should use
throughout your entire onboarding even
is that people don't read so if you have
a lot to
say a long pay wall can work especially
for a hard pay wall because then people
maybe will take the time to scroll if
you have a hard pay wall and they don't
have an option but to read but if you
don't have a hard pay wall especially
and it's a premium product and you have
a lot you want to communicate
communicating in smaller chunks that are
easier to digest in multiple steps is a
great way to take the things that you
would think should be on the pay wall
but can actually be kind of one at a
time stepped through in a way that and
you were saying this earlier is with the
first gem from Daryl about what's
leading up to the pay wall is that this
is like the perfect example of like
really controlling those last few steps
before the paywall with like really
strong message meing and again messaging
that you maybe think should be on the
pay wall but by putting it in individual
Pages it can just be so much more
impactful and the choice between long
pay and multic Screen I mean that's
something you you want to test but I
agree if you have a long pay well you're
typically going to get only the real
explorers scrolling down and dividing it
it pces is usually helpful to get people
to really see it also an often main
mistake is you know your plans are not
above the fold if you had a long Pall
cuz you decided to put too much stuff on
it and and then you miss out this is
actually fairly easy to test so if you
currently have a long pay wall take that
pay wall break it up into three or four
pages and experiment with the
multi-stage pay wall because you might
be surprised just how well that performs
compared to the long pay wall 100% all
right next gem next gem is from Toma P
Favorite growth consultant it's the
conversion behavior of users during
onboarding and post onboarding is
different so you probably want a
different bill for the two when you AB
test your pay wall separate the analysis
between the onboarding pay wall and the
post onboarding pay walls and I like it
because typically you think one pay wall
but you essentially display it in a
bunch of places so you can make one
change to your pay wall that's going to
help right at the end of the onboarding
or even during onboarding but that can
hurt after and same thing can be true
the opposite if you start showing that
free versus pay chart on your first pay
wall then you're probably going to hurt
yourself but if you use it as a second
pay wall later on when some people
access a feature you're actually helping
them understand what they could get in
addition because they'll probably
already know to some extent what they
can get for free since they did not
convert initially now I have a caveat on
on that one is that if you're starting
if you're early stage if you're not
super sophisticated you probably don't
want to bother with that because chances
are you have 80% of your conversions on
the first day allall and and diving into
optimizing you know the remaining 20% is
probably not the best effort you can put
to increase LTV and conversions in
general this can be relatively low
hanging fruit though so like if you do
have a pay wall that has a description
of each of your main premium features
then just remixing that one pay wall to
focus on each of the premium features so
that when a user Taps on that specific
feature they see kind of the pitch for
that feature more prominently those kind
of things can probably be done fairly
straight forward so maybe there's ways
to maybe do it easier and less
sophisticated and still make it work but
I think you're totally right it's like
it's too easy to get lost in the weeds
and like spend way too much time over
optimizing when you're early you know if
you're making 100K a month or more it's
like these are the kind of things that
are going to help you get from 100 to
200 to 500 to a million is starting to
optimize things like this yeah in the
end you need to to do the math little
rise prioritization and see if that's
let's say a better opportunity than
changing something in your own Bing and
maybe it depends you know if you have
reue C and it's easy to do then yeah if
there's an effort that's limited so you
can turn that over pretty quickly you
actually set up things very nicely for
the next gem with about impulse it's
from the 2.5 Gamers show and it was
mostly J RR that was presenting it it's
create feature SL qu/ report specific
pay Wells focusing on what the user
could get based on what triggered the
pay well when they Clos the the specific
payall show popup telling them about all
the benefits they get with premium
access if they decline again give them
the option to access the initial feature
for I AP so it's essentially a
multi-layer thing where you saw a
specific feature you click on it and you
get a p that's specific to that content
you try to access is unlock it with
premium but if you don't unlock it you
reiterate everything else you can get
with premium so you have essentially a
second pill that says here's everything
else you can get with premium and if
they close it then you have an i AP and
you have purchase to give them access
just to that one feature or piece of
content and so you piece it like that to
hopefully increase conversion and target
people you know alongside the demand
curve yeah I really like this one and at
upth annual and we weren't able to share
the recording but at appgrowth annual
employee from Google Tammy was sharing
how much Google is seeing apps that use
hybrid monetization have been really
succeeding and I think this is something
folks who are focused on iOS can
actually learn from Android and it might
be just as impactful if not more on iOS
and that's this idea of hybrid
monetization is like if somebody is
willing to pay for something but they're
not quite ready to pay for the whole
experience and subscribe and have
recurring payments you know some people
are just not wanting to subscribe you
know they have so many subscriptions
even when you have a ton of
subscriptions if you find it valuable
you're going to pay but then they might
be enticed by the single in app
purchases so again probably not
something early stage that you want to
get too sophisticated with to your point
earlier but it can be a powerful unlock
to get them to pay experience the value
and then want more so yeah I think it's
fantastic yeah with exactly that same
caveat on on your growth stage it
absolutely might not be the thing you
want to focus on if you're early and
same thing goes with you know anything
you're price testing to death and
haven't tested anything else you're
missing out so you need to go in areas
where you don't have diminishing returns
or where you have big opportunities all
right what's the next gem the next gem
is also from tomap and it's
aggressiveness of monetization comes in
many different shades and those tricks
often work so you can have free tral
toggles Wheel of Fortune on or after the
pay well backup offers but you need to
find the B so you don't give an overall
scammy feeling and we end with kind of
firming the discussion again is like how
many of the tricks are you going to
layer into your app and how much is that
in line with your app its concept your
audience or how much is that going to
maybe annoy them and deteriorate their
brain perception yeah I've been thinking
a lot about this I actually recently did
a podcast with a golfing app and I loved
the way Alex the CEO there framed being
more conscientious of your users and the
example he gave was that he actually has
imaginary conversations with users in
his head anytime he's writing copy
building features going through flows
this is a perfect example of like if
somebody walks into a golf shop they
would expect somebody to walk up and say
hey what are you interested in today you
looking for clubs you need some balls
that's expected right and that's not
annoying when somebody asks hey you need
some help but then if you say oh no I'm
just browsing and they're like oh we
have this and oh we have that and
they'll follow you around the store
that's awkward right that's the
experience we don't like as humans and
so I think this is actually a really
good analogy to draw go through your own
onboarding and have a conversation in
your head with the user this page says
that how does that make the user feel
what do they say if I'm talking to
another human being or roleplay with
colleagues or something and how does it
feel going through all this and I think
this point from Thomas and the way you
shared it is really good that if you
layer on too many of these it starts to
feel like that uh used car
salesman and if you're spending a ton of
money on ads and you got to hit that row
as and the brand isn't important to you
you're okay with higher turn or whatever
maybe you do layer on a bunch of these
together and it just it is what it is it
can be very effective but I think you
need to do that kind of with full
realization of how you make your users
feel and then what that means to the
long-term performance of the business
and so if you're using all of these
tactics and laying on so many you should
expect higher turn because you're doing
kind of a high pressure sale which then
leaves the user not as fond of the brand
and maybe a little more on edge so yeah
I think this I think is a a fantastic
way to kind of wrap up this whole pay
wall optimization conversation is that
you can't go too far and that that may
not be good for the business even if the
ab test is successful yeah I mean if
it's a s you're running out of Runway
and and you have to close shot then then
yes you know the the the choice is
easier but also even for the same tactic
the implementation matters so much I'll
take two examples this you know the
example of endle which I believe is an
app where you can listen to sounds to
focus Etc and the way they did they
gamify their offer is you choose I think
you try to find in which tra there's an
apple and or you choose one of the trees
within an apple and like it gives you a
discount and like I I don't really see
the connection and I was a little
confused and I was not expecting that in
in that app but you take Cal's
implementation of kind of the daily gift
the way they did it you have a
meditation bow and you have to go with
your finger around the bowl and that
kind of triggers you know the spinning
the wheel motion but there's no wheel
it's it's just a ball and it's very much
in line with you know the concept of
meditating so it's it's a much softer
implementation than let's say a spin the
wheel gamified offer
awesome well syvan this has been so much
fun chatting through these gems anything
you wanted to share as we wrapped up no
I mean go visit grow jams on suback
subscribe to the newsletter I have
awesome content coming up I think it's
going to become a must read for anybody
in subscription apps so go check it out
awesome thanks so much for joining me
today have a good
one thanks so much for listening if you
have a minute please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player you can
also stop by chat. subclub docomo our
private community
[Music]